Jordan thank you so much for giving us some time again. I'm in Sydney. You're in Kentucky. Yes, I am
I'm there as part of my 12 rules for life tour
Which is I think expanding to hit about maybe 80 cities something like that
Goodness. Well, that was very keen to have a follow-up chat after the conversation that you and I had together when you're in Sydney
And in particular to frame that for people who might be listening this conversation at that time
I had not seen you in front of a live audience
The evening of that conversation after that conversation. I had that opportunity at Chatswood one of the
seven talks that you gave in Australia put together by Sam McClelland from
From Melbourne every one of them are sellout
I have to say I don't know whether the biggest issue for me is what I learnt by watching that all the questions that arise
out of it
But the first thing I'd say is I was concerned at the time
That you and I had had a very long conversation that it might be too long for people when we put it on the website
And you said no John? It won't be young people especially are hungry for content. Put it all up there
They will listen to it. You're absolutely right young people looking for content
It's it is absolutely amazing. Yes. Well, I mean some of the big YouTube stars like Joe Rogan
They're they're constantly putting out three-hour podcasts and people listen to all of them long-haul truckers
listen to them and guys driving forklifts and and young people and and couples and
Like there's a massive hunger for real for ready for high-quality educational material
It shouldn't be underestimated
and I mean one of the things that seems to be the case with these people on YouTube that are making a
splash let's say in this alternate media format is that
they fully they have full respect for the or the intelligence of their audience and they don't pull any punches in terms of content or
length
Yeah, well, that's where they come back to that
but but as I say, you know
It's just extraordinary I pull up in a fuel station out in a country town near where I live
And somebody gets out of the car next to me father of about
35 I suppose he looks at me and he just says straight up before even says hello
he said I've just been listening to you and Jordan Peterson having a conversation and
Everywhere I go now. That's what people say. So thank you for the opportunity. You made the comment there though there for every youtube
Visit they'd be up to 11 podcasts. I think that's what you said
well
the podcast market is absolutely exploding and you're actually sitting seeing this start to affect book publishing because
audio books have become extraordinarily popular and people are discovering that they can use their found time when they're commuting or
Exercising or walking or doing dishes whatever to engage themselves in high quality. Um
well high quality educational material books and podcasts and so that's a real revolution it and it really is a
revolution
So these are the people young people too, you know instead of listening to music
Which is really something because musics being a predominant cultural force for a very long time
So it's an it's an amazing technological revolution and I really appreciate it or a conversation by the way
I think we had a great conversation
I enjoyed it immensely
And it seems to me that this is a sort of modern version and and I think this is terrific if I'm understanding it correctly
Or the old idea where people who have perhaps had another great formal education had access to good quality
Literature and so forth put together by whether it was penguin or what. Was it every man's book
So every everyday books whatever they were called even Reader's Digest
To make that education that learning the classics and so forth available widely
And now this is a modern version of it perhaps and I think what's happening with the mainstream mean?
that they underestimate the
Moral quality of their viewers, they underestimate their intelligence. They underestimate their persistence and
they've also become quite manipulative in their use of editing and and message
Massaging spin really and the other thing that's really good about these sorts of conversations
Is that what you see is what you get their bare bones
They're they're not high-tech while they are and their highest tech in some sense, but not on the production end or the editing end
So people can trust them and they're genuine conversations. They're not designed to craft the message or anything like that
They're not manipulative and and that's a big deal
YouTube YouTube
Particularly doesn't respond well to manipulation as far as I can tell. Well, I enjoyed that conversation enormously. I've been stunned by the response
It's gone very very widely as you know
Both on your site and on mine
But to come back to that day
later that day you gave one of the talks of the set one of the seven that you gave in Australia Chatswood and
I was very kindly
allowed to compare it for you and
One thing that 19 years in public life taught me is to have a bit of a look at your audience and summarize them
It was a pretty amazing experience. The first thing that happened was that you walked on before you said a word
You've got a standing ovation though that that's something unheard of in this country, but they did
90 minutes talk they gave you another standing ovation
you left came for a few minutes came back on took 30 minutes of questions and
Again, they responded in the same way. Let me just say a couple of things about that audience. I was
firstly I've got to say pretty heavily impacted as I looked out there and
Recognized that there was an enormous hunger to hear what you had to say
Even though your message was perhaps best described as tough. Love you weren't
Ginger in them up with a soft story. You were really pushing you were really challenging them
The second thing that struck me is that I've said many times since I reckon
50% of the people in that room that night were young Australian men under the age of probably 35
The third thing that struck me was that that was a was a cross section
I would say many of them were University students, but all university graduates
But many many were not and the fourth thing that just goes back to something. You said a moment ago
They knew what you were saying and you're a clinical psychologist and a highly educated
Person to suggest that they didn't understand would be very patronizing they got what you're on about. Oh, definitely
There's there's no doubt about that
I mean there those lectures aren't interesting unless you understand them and there's just no doubt that that's happening
you know, I think one of the most that
psychologists have made
Especially the more popular ones over the last three or four decades is to try to convince people that they're okay the way they are
It's like the self-esteem movement, you know, you should love yourself the way they you are
You should feel good about yourself the way you are and that's actually not a very optimistic
Message for people because people are generally sensible enough to not be particularly satisfied with the way that they are
They want to be who they could be
they want to have something noble to aim at and and and
So I I make that case very strong that you're you should more
but aligned and on board with who you can be then with who you are and
that who you can be isn't a person who has endless rights or
Or or as the member of a privileged or under privileged group
It should be who you should be should be an individual who's willing to take on full
responsibility for the for the catastrophe of existence and for the malevolence that's part of it and
See, I think people are responding to that
first of all because everyone who has any sense knows that life is a tragic business and that everyone is
Susceptible to betrayal and malevolence on their own part and and as a consequence of the actions of others, that's our existential
Predicament and I think people also know in a very deep sense that the antidote to that isn't security or safety
And it's not envy or bitterness. It's the willingness to
try to work to make the world a better place to start with yourself to take responsibility for yourself and then to take
responsibility for your family and then to take
responsibility for your community and everyone knows that the people they admire are exactly the people that do that and
We also all know that that's what gets you out of bed on a rough morning
It's that you've got something important and vital to do and it's not an easy thing
It isn't necessarily even something that makes you happy
It's something that's meaningful and necessary to fight back against the tragedy and the malevolence of the world and people know that
Deeply it's deeply rooted inside their their souls. I would say and a call to that is
very meaningful for people including me, you know, I include myself and my audience like I'm
Lecturing to them precisely. I'm having a conversation with them about how we can step the world
right
And we are setting it right things are getting better very rapidly around the world and we can really push that forward in the decades
To come if we if we made a conscious effort and so I think this is a very exciting message for people
One of the things that I'd say about Australians is as I got the world's best bulldust detectors. They
recognise authentic authenticity
Very quickly, and if you're not authentic, they won't listen
So I think in part they are responding if I can pay you a compliment by the fact that you weren't talking about you
You were talking about us
You were addressing
Where we are all together as human beings and in a way it was as though you were saying
To get to the good news
You've actually got to go through what might be called the valley of death. You've got to face yourself
You've got to be realistic about yourself in the world that you live in
And I saw those put young people
It was almost as though they were saying we're sick to death of a therapy cup a culture that offers us sort of
To relieve to everyone there's a there's a dictum
that Carl Jung derived from the great alchemists in the circle in this infinite or and it means
What you most want will be found where you least want to look?
What you most need will be found where you least want to look and that people know that you know
everyone knows they are tired of
naive
Optimism let's say and not optimism because optimism doesn't have to be naive and they know perfectly
well that the way to set themselves right is to take careful stock of themselves and to pay very
careful attention to the errors that they know they're making and to and to grow up and to mature and to and to
adopt the responsibilities of a forthright citizen and I think people are sick to death of too much discussion of rights and and
too much discussion of self-esteem and all that all that all
That discussion that goes along with what everyone owes you it's like
it's just not helpful to people because it isn't your rights that give you meaning in life and
You need a meaning to set against the tragedy and every knows that the way that you find that meaning. It's by adopting responsibility, obviously
For yourself, you gotta take care of yourself your family
I mean you want to be a good person to your parents. You want to be a good person to your siblings and your children
Clearly and you have to bear some responsibility for your community
And if you're really firing on all cylinders, you do all those things at the same time
You know and and I do believe and I tell people I do believe that the world is the tragic and malevolent place in many
many ways but that the way forward through that is is to
Do everything you can to put yourself on the side of what's good and to aim high and that that's where you get the dignity
That enables you to bear life without becoming corrupt and everyone knows this is true
Who's gonna argue with that?
having found yourself and having any of your like and being realistic about yourself and
Recognizing we were talking about this last time the dividing line between good and evil. It's not between black and white or whatever
captor and jailer
Or man and woman
It's somewhere across every human heart having recognized that you can then go on and help build a stronger fairer more just more humane
society rather than
what seems to be the way people approach it at the moment so
That somehow rather your society can fix your problems. Yes. Well, that's it
I mean for young people in particular, it's kits are actually a very depressing message for young people to hear that
It's time for them to get involved in political activism because any young person who has any sense knows perfectly
Well, if they're especially if they're 18, they're so 19 years old is they don't know a damn thing, you know
They haven't started a business. They haven't started a family. They don't have a permanent relationship. They're not educated
They don't have any experience and for someone to come and say well you're in a position to change the world is
nothing, but a way of
Disenchanting them with adult wisdom. It's like you're not ready to change the world
You've got a lot to learn but you can learn it and in learning it you'll become much more powerful and much more
Charismatic and much more articulate and much more wise and sensible and that's the way forward
to being much more than you are and
young people when you're 18 and you have 60 years of life ahead of you what you want to hear above all else is that
There's way more of you yet to come
Because what else has anything with those 60 years
so
It's it's a message. It's a harsh message because it says well
You're not everything you could be but it's a deeply optimistic message because it's because the idea is that you could be way more
Than you are
incomparably more than you are and I do believe that and what's so fun about this is that people keep telling me that people
Keep telling me that it's true. You know, I have people
Endless people I got one kid come up to me the other day. It was so fun
He said a year and a half ago. I had just got out of jail and I was homeless
And he said I started listening to your lectures and I just I got married this year
I have a child and I just bought my apartment. It's like wow man. Good work
You know you did that in a year and a half
And you know, I was in LA the other about a month ago and you know this I was in a rough part of LA
Downtown LA near the Apollo Theater, and I'd given a talk there my wife and I were walking down the street
This car pick pulled up and then his kid walked out. He was about 19 or so
Good-looking Hispanic kid ran over and asked me if I was dr. Peters and I said yes, and he was all excited
He said he'd been watching my videos for about a year and a half and they really helped him straighten out his life
He was just smiling away
He said wait a minute
wait a minute and he ran back to his car and he came back out with his dad and
His dad was standing there
you know and they had their arms around each other and
They were just grinning like mad and the kid said look
I've really put my relationship together with my father and we're really on board with this together
And they were just like so happy you couldn't believe it and that just happens over and over like it happens. I would say
four or five times a day in restaurants or in airports or while you've been
experiencing that to some degree in Australia you said and it's it's so good and
The mainstream media that's been covering what I've been doing, you know
they just missed this completely because everything it seems like everything that constitutes news in our society has to be
Political and group oriented this isn't political and it's not group oriented what I'm trying to do as a good clinical
Psychologist and perhaps a good educator and I mean good striving to be good in the moral sense is to help people
develop as individuals and they are and
it's really working and it's it's a thrill to be on this tour because that's all I hear and
no one talks to me about the political issues or very very rarely and it's all because I also think that the battle against
Collectivists and let's say the battle against identity politics isn't to be had in the political realm
maybe that's a secondary issue what the way that you that you
fight for the sovereignty of the individual is by getting your act together and and right locally right where you are and
starting to take advantage of everything that you have in front of you and
And then you do, you know harm our way. All you do is make yourself less bad. Who what's the harm?
Not that's a good thing to some extent
I think the battle here is almost one of statism or collectivism versus individual liberty who's going to shape who?
So you've got the whole that sort of pushed from the left identity politics victimhood policies
Approaches and what have you we owe these people? What have you?
So the state has control and shapes individuals and helps them forward on the other hand
You have the different view that says no the state should be shaped by the people that make up the state, you know
Australia is a sum total of individuals who are Australian and they ought to be
Shaping the public square not having the public square of your local the public sector shaping them
The whole argument is about what what what's the primary unit of analysis? That's everything
What's the primary unit of analysis and in the West the primary unit of the analysis has been the logos and that's something like Devine?
individual consciousness and it's on that ground that we developed our idea of individual sovereignty and citizenship and
you know, we don't talk about a citizen is someone who adopts the
Responsibilities of an ethical being that's a citizen. We don't talk about that even in schools
Tell people that look the meaning in your life is going to be found
It's gonna be proportionate to the degree that you take responsibility for
Positively shaping your experience and the experience of the people around you and this isn't like be good in some in some week
Be inoffensive and harmless sense. It's not that at all
It's like get your spine straight get your aggression
integrated pick a heavy goal like a heavy high goal something you can barely tolerate lifting and
struggle along with it and that's where you'll find yourself respect and and people know that it's it's fun to watch the
Working-class guys respond to this too, you know because they know this most of those guys work like mad, you know
and they know that there's nobility in that and and there is and so
It's it's well
I'm people also say well that they're happy to come to my lectures or even read the book because
I'm helping them find words to express things that they already knew to be true and
those things that they know to be true are the
Bedrock axioms of our culture and one of the things we got right in the West was the idea of the sovereign
Responsible individual not the person with rights and certainly not the person with rights granted to them by the state
That's not part of the English common law tradition. You're the locus of Rights
But but only in some sense because you're the locus of ultimate responsibility. I
Guess part of what I've been trying to tell people is that there's no difference between meaning and responsibility
They're the same thing. Yeah. No, I understand what you're saying. Now as I looked at that audience. I thought to myself
We're doing a lot of talking about the first world war in this country
60 thousand Australians died out of a very small population in that horrendous event and we celebrate their bravery those young
Anzacs we call them who went off to
Gallipoli and then to the Western Front and we're involved in some of the critical battles of the First World War
every year
Australians turn out in extraordinary numbers and more and more young Australians turn out to if you like pay tribute to their
Courage and as I looked out across that audience, I thought there's a lot of people here that I'd willingly
Or I would choose to be with in the trenches
They are essentially people who want to be to use the word. You did just a moment ago
Noble to the best of their ability
But they live in a culture somehow that says no that's all nonsense
that's not where you ought to go and
It seemed to me that they're deeply resenting and deeply keen to reject that approach. Look here's here's what it is
so there's this idea that
That's pushed very hard in the Universities by the postmodern neo-marxist types and before anybody objects
I know perfectly. Well that technically speaking post-modernism and neo-marxist neo Marxism aren't commensurate
But it doesn't stop people from from joining them together
Ideologically, but in any case the idea is that the West is fundamentally an oppressive patriarchy
which it isn't it's hardly an oppressive society because every society is partly oppressive and flawed, but
fundamentally, the West is not an oppressive patriarchy and but if you by that line then the next thing that comes along is that
Anything you do that?
contributes to that
Patriarchy is also oppressive and tyrannical and so that's extraordinarily
demoralizing for people who are trying to make their way in the world because they're trying to
Hoist their responsibilities up on their shoulders and become competent
Contributing adults and they're criticized to death for being oppressive tyrants
And so there's a conflation of competence with tyranny and you can't do anything to anyone that's more demoralizing that you know than that
Nietzsche said if you want to punish someone punish
Them for their virtues and so they're tired of that. It's so demoralizing
You know, like it appeals to the part of each man. Let's say and each woman for that matter who wants to avoid responsibility
because you can rationalize it and say well I'm not gonna take responsibility because that just makes me a
tyrant and an agent of the
Patriarchy, but that's a-- that sort of thing leads people down at toolpath and I've seen that my my friends and in my clinical practice
So instead we say look like our culture has problems every culture does and it needs everyone
Everyone has to be awake so that we don't slip at every level of our social being into some like a blind
authoritarianism, but the way that that happens is by waking up and taking responsibility once again for yourself and your family and
Your community and that that and that's Noble which is a word you never hear
It's like a human being has to be a noble creature to withstand the tragedy of existence without becoming corrupt
and so and that calls to the best in people and
Jordan just we should wrap up on that part of it that evening though, but there was one other thing
When we came to question time, there were four mics in the room. They lined up 20 deeper deets
We got to seven. I think the seventh question was from a lady who asked a very intelligent question about what?
Parents bring to their children and and in particular
were there things that mothers brought to their children that women do best and other things that
fathers bring to their children that are best you gave a very rousing answer the issue of fathering and as I say,
There are a lot of men there
I gather that your audiences of the demographics have broadened out now, but that was a very young man centric
group
And you hammered the importance as I heard it all fathering
Well, the the empirical literature on this is absolutely clear
I mean, you know, we have this idea that's being pushed forward that all families are equal. It's like
There's a there's a grain of truth in that in that people who are struggling
Mightily to raise their children properly are worthy of respect whether there are single or in couples
but the empirical literature is absolutely clear that that stable intact for the
families with fathers there produce children who do way better on almost every possible measure and even more than that that
in communities where
fathers tend to be at home
What you know as part of the stable family the communities themselves do better even those kids that don't have fathers at home
So the role of the father is unbelievably important and the question is what particular rold as a father plan
I just had a good conversation with Warren Farrell about that and part of no part of my research should indicated that
men are particularly useful in initiating
Rough-and-tumble play and play with their children in general and Farrell extended that by noting that men could use the opportunity
to play as a reward for delaying gratification
among their children
That's a really big deal because one of the things you have to do to help people mature is to teach them to delay gratification
and to sustain attention and it looks like
Men that the pleasure that children get in playing with their fathers
Rough and tumble play but other forms of play as well
Of primary reward that can be used to help children learn to make the proper sacrifices and regulate their impulses over the long term
so
So, you know and I think fathers now of course mothers can do this too, but I think fathers
Are because mothers are generally charged with the fundamental care of infants. There's a tension between that and
encouraging children to step forward out into the world as as
Courageous beings and you know mothers are very very attached to their infants and their infants are very fragile
it's often hard for them to make the transition from
primary
security provider and caregiver to
forthright encourage
er of adventure and that's certainly something that fathers can do is
It's better to construe life as an adventure rather than as an enterprise that's there to make you feel secure or happy
It's a great adventure and a dangerous one at that because everyone's life is at stake in this adventure
You know, we're unbelievably tough creatures if we if we put ourselves out fully
Okay, now you said something very interesting there and very important in my view you talked about empirical evidence in the relation to the importance
of fathering
empirical evidence
reason
evidence-based decision-making
calm
thoughtful deliberation rather than emotion in other words the difference between thinking and
Feeling seems to me to be incredibly important
We should follow the facts to where they take us, but we're confronted by it seems to be you mentioned
and you said they're not related but we tie them together there, you know sort of cultural Marxism and
post-modernism it seems to me the cultural Marxist will deliberately distort the truth be
because of their agendas or hide the truth because of their agendas the post modernists are fallen into this trap of
If you like moral relativity, so what's good for you is true for you
And what's good for me is true for me. Even if they're really painting black as white and white as black
Isn't that a problem?
It's worse than that in some sense because it's not even what's true for you
It's true for you. And what's true for me is true for me
It's what it's true for your group is only good for your group
And what's true for my group is only good for my group
And so that sets us off in in group conflict in a tribal sort of way. You know the the
the real radical types who are swallowed up by this ideology believe that science itself is nothing but a Eurocentric
Patriarchal construct. I mean they dispense completely with the fact that
Scientific discovery has given us this incredible
Technological power that's lifted the entire world out of abject poverty in a period of about a hundred and fifty years
For that for them for some reason that doesn't constitute evidence
and so when you bring up evidence
There's hand waving because the people who dispute this sort of thing rarely know the details of the literature
They just write it off and say well that whole scientific enterprise that's just part of the way that Eurocentric males
dominate and destroyed the planet
It's all power games for these people. There's no there's no reality at the bottom of it outside of the power game
And so that's a well
That that to me that that that's a that's a viewpoint that leads inevitably to tribal conflict
That's all that's all that's what it does know. You might be able to help me
I think was George Orwell who made a reference to an idea being so utterly stupid that only a member of the intelligentsia could believe
It no sensible person in the street would accept it for a moment
There was a bit of there that night I would have thought you actually made a comment
quite a I thought a very astute remark that about something that sound absolutely obvious and then you father finished it by saying you
Would have thought someone in a university somewhere might have noticed now if I'd been an academic at any university in Australia
I would have realized that I needed to wake up to myself because the audience lifted the roof the place with their applause they are
highly skeptical about what is happening now in our educational institutions
There is no other way to read that audience of a thousand decent Australians
They are very skeptical about the value for money. We're getting now out of our tertiary education sector
Yeah, well, it's the whole education sector to I would say increasingly from kindergarten all the way through University
Yeah
I think that I'm in very in creasing lis embarrassed to be a member of the Academy
Because of that like I was reading this book today by a by a Norwegian called progress. It's a really good book
I would highly recommend it very straightforward and all it is is a compendium of
empirical facts about how much better the world has been getting for the last
Hundred and fifty years in just every possible way three hundred thousand people a week are being hooked to the electrical power
Grid, right we've reduced we've almost eliminated
Starvation throughout the world except for political reasons and starvation was a big problem in places like Sweden and Italy
Less than a hundred years ago
Island
People our people have access to fresh water and the fastest growing economies in the world are in sub-saharan Africa
We're just making progress progress on every possible front and everything
that people learn in the education system seems to be associated with the idea that
human beings are a cancerous growth on the
planet that we're going to hell in a handbasket and that we're gonna burn ourselves out in the next 50 years and die and
It'll be our fault too. And you know, it's just not the case. It's simply not the case
I mean we have problems in front of us, but there's a deep anti human ethos that permeates that and you know
Maybe it's still a hangover from our pessimism from the Cold War
You know because everyone was truly terrified for about five decades that we were gonna put everything to the torch, you know
and maybe we still haven't really recovered from that and it's not surprising because it was brutal, but
Reading this book on progress just made me think again. How badly were
Educated because people just don't know how much things are getting better and why?
Free markets are a huge part of it private property is a huge part of it
And that's all associated with the idea of the sovereign individual. And so this really works
I mean, it's true that Europe got rich first, but that's only being a hundred and most at most one hundred and fifty years
It's not even that long. It's really since about 1895 and Europe first, but man China there's no one starving in China
There's no one starving in India
You know Southeast Asia
has enough food and and
Sub-saharan Africa is growing like mad
And then that we have these we have these we have our education system that trumpets that you know
we live in a corrupt patriarchy that we should all identify with our tribal groups and that the right way of
Interviewing history is victimizer group against victim group. It's like it's no wonder people are skeptical about it
It's a profoundly anti Western ethos. And the thing is about the West is we got the sovereign individual, right?
It's right and it's the responsibility part. That's right. Not the rights part. I mean the rights traits are necessary. But but only
The rights are there so that you couldn't express your responsibility. That's what that's the whole point
Okay, well let's come to this issue of our own almost loathing now of our own beliefs and values
here in Australia now, we're having an extraordinary debate going on a very wealthy and
Likable, I knew him well philanthropists called Paul Ramsey who was very active in the health center
Left a very large amount of money to be made available to set up
An academy for the study of Western civilization and he wanted it to be done in one of our major
universities now one of our most acclaimed universities
Entered into deep negotiations then the education union got involved and said no. No, this is going to be terrible. It'll be all about European
Ideas of European supremacy so that same university has centers for Islamic studies for Indigenous Studies
They are not particularly autonomous in the sense that the university or sorry. They're not particularly controlled
It seems by the university
They do pretty much their own thing, but I know you can't have a center for the study of Western civilization
It will fill us up with all sorts of racist ideas
Supremacist ideas. This is really worrying if we can't understand our own past
In fact as a very wise Asian said here the other day
If you wonder them that want to understand Asian cultures understand your your own first
Well, it means to me it's just first of all, you know in some sense
I'm less worried about what's happening with the universities than I was because I think that
They're going to destroy themselves
completely if they continue the way they are and that all that's going to happen is that people will take the genuine value in the
Wisdom of the past and presented in alternative forms, they'll just steal it out from underneath the universities
I would say to the philanthropist if the universities don't want the money then they should set up an institute on their own
That might very well be a good course
You can go directly to the people now, you know, like for now a social example for me if I want a lecture now
I can lecture on anything I want
Whenever I want with no bureaucratic restrictions
And I have an audience of people who are only listening because they want to listen
There that's where the university is
The University is where there's an audience to people who are only listening because they want to be educated
That is the University. The buildings are irrelevant
Let's let's build on that from I'm it because watching this debate unfold in Australia
We're listening your academic saying ah, no. No, we've got to preserve our academic integrity
And we've we're here to protect
policies of diversity and inclusiveness
And all of those sorts of things and somebody tartly pointed out
Actually, we thought they were there to teach our young people how to think for themselves
Primarily that isn't what they're there for because that's predicated on the idea that there are sovereign
Individuals and that they can actually think for themselves as individuals
The whole idea here is that you're not an individual. You're the member of a group that's it, and they're serious about this
This isn't a trivial objection. It's a fundamental objection, but I would also say look there's a New Testament
Statement don't cast pearls before swine and you know that usually has to do with words
Right don't waste words of wisdom on those who will not hear but you could also just look at it
literally if you have pearls and you're trying to give them to someone
and they won't take them then go find someone else to give the pearls to if you're trying to give money to a
University to do something great and they won't take it. It's obvious that they don't want to do anything great
So don't give them the money. It's the wrong people
Ok, well, let's taste this had a little bit more
wisdom, you've mentioned the difference between
if you like knowledge and
accumulated cleverness
and what have you and
wisdom
Surely there's a difference because to go back again to Chatswood
I would say a good chunk of the people there were not university educated
But they were smart and I would say they I'd say more they were wise
They were striving for wisdom. And that's where wisdom is wisdom is in the striving for wisdom and wisdom is building out
Wisdom isn't a collection of facts wisdom is knowledge of how to conduct yourself in the world
So it's a it's an action. It's an existential issue. It's an it's its truth as revealed in action. That's wisdom
wisdom also understands consequences
Well, it's it's sophisticated in its understanding of consequences because you think well
What are the consequences and the answer is well?
There's the consequences for you now and for you next week and next month and five years from now
So the consequences are you and future you so that's an iterated game
but the consequences are also for your family now and in the future transfer to your community now and in the future and
wisdom is the ability to consider all of those consequences as part of your as
part of what guides your vision and your and your and your operations in the world and that's character and
Then nobility of character is to take all of those things into account
simultaneously as I watch the debate
I thought to some extent one of the problems you've got here is see as Lewis might have pointed out is pride
Pride getting in the way of people having sufficient humility to recognize
That the nonsense they peddling is simply unconvincing in terms of what you might call the pub test
What would pass the pub test?
Out there where people have common sense and can see when people are being real and when they're not being real
Well, it's easy to dispense with that
You just develop sufficient contempt for the common person and then you don't have to worry about what they think
You know and then and that's and that's when you confuse being smart with being wise and they're not the same thing
I don't think there's any relationship between them
In fact, I mean intelligence is a great gift
But it can go terribly wrong and it can certainly turn into a kind of intellectual arrogance
that's for sure that blinds you to to your own ignorance and humility is the antidote to that and the
humility the element of humility there that's necessary is to understand that what you don't know is more important than what you know, and
So if you're an ideologue you you dispense with all doubt because you already know everything I was
gonna say I was reminded of that friend I
Chatswood as as you probably gathered it had the big impact on man. It was a powerful reminder to me that
For me, it seems very important to recognize it. There's a sense in which the more you learn the more you realizes
You don't know very much and there's a lot more to learn
Yeah, well
You know being with an audience can help with it out, too
Because if you're if you're talking to an audience, you can check to see if your message is being received, you know
And you might say well these people just can't understand what I have to say
It's like well, yeah
They probably can if you if you formulated it carefully
And you actually talk to them individual to individual which is what I try to do in my lectures
Like I'm not talking to the mob. I'm not talking to the group. I never talked to the group when I'm lecturing
I always pick people in the audience and speak right to them and they reflect the audit, you know, they reflect the entire group
But they only reflect it because the group is made up of individuals like them
So let's just go back to something. You said earlier that ask of me is very interesting
And that is that young people don't want to be involved in political activism
They want to get himself sorted out first many of those young people though
I think want to behave nobly and help build a better society a stronger civic square if I can put it that way and
Good on them. That's terrific. That's important
They're very disillusioned with politics and yet we have to govern our country
We have to make certain the rules are set if you like
And that we maximize everybody's opportunities to live in freedom and insecurity
When young people have if you like grounded themselves and feel ready to act nobly in the public square
What should they do? How can they make a difference they want to make a difference? How do they go about it Oh
More power to them I think but I think you know
They they start by realizing they don't know anything and by starting to learn and then if they learn and work and discipline themselves
The opportunities to expand will come naturally because people will notice them
Like look if you work with competent people hyper competent people one of the things you learn is that hyper competent
People are always looking for young people to mentor
Yeah
there's starving and
Hoping that someone will come along who who has a lot of potential and then what they'll do is offer them an opportunity
Hmm, you know, I keep my eye out at the University and in my private work as well all the time for young people
Who've got something to contribute. Oh, you look like you're sharp. Let's find out. Here's a task
Why don't you go try this then they come back and knock it out of the park. And you think oh, that's good
Cuz I got 20 more things here that need doing that
I can't do I've got more opportunities than I know what to do with here's another one
and so the thing is is that if you develop your competence and you discipline yourself and you start to make that manifest in any
Hierarchy that's even vaguely competent. You'll have more opportunities come your way. Then you'll know what to do with
So it'll happen organically
so and it it is the way of the world and
well
if that isn't happening in the organization that you're working with and you're
Working diligently and you have your art together, then it's time to find a different organization
But generally speaking most organizations aren't that corrupt? Some are
interesting, I'd say that
Australia's, have we worship youth culture in a way?
but well things I've noticed about youth is that
Overwhelmingly if I have the opportunity to tap into the wisdom of an older person to be mentored they they go looking for it
They're very keen for it
Well, it's part of the part of the human
Proclivity to admire and imitate, you know, I mean one of the things that drives us forward
We don't only learn by facts. In fact, we hardly learn by facts at all. We learn by
Stories and we learn by imitation and we and may imitate those we admire and we admire those who are competent
and
So if you find someone who knows what you don't and can operate effectively
in the world in a manner that you would like to but can't then you're going to admire them and if you admire them you're
Going to open the door to have them mentor you and I mean that's that's really fundamental to human cognition and human psychological
Development it's the catalyst for human development because we're deeply imitative
It's it's the thing that distinguishes us from other creatures
Perhaps even more than even more fundamentally than language use
if I watch if you know how to do something and I watch you do it I
Can learn to do it without having to go through all the pain that you had to go through to learn it
It's such a gift
That's why history is so important our personal history
Our if you like our family history
I was thinking the other day that my grandfather made a mistake with my father on the farm that I am determined
Because I can learn from that not to repeat with my own son on the farm
And then there's of course the broader cultural history
which is why I believe and I think you win it you and I share this view we ought to learn from our history we
ought to learn from the horrors of
Collectivism in Soviet Russia, we ought to be honest about it
We should teach our young people at the same time as we're honest about the what's in our own cultural history
But we're also honest about the nobility
For example the mighty push to abolish slavery surely the greatest human rights movement of all times. We ought to know about it
It's Noble. It was led by noble people who struggled against extraordinary odds for a long time
Yes, exactly and slavery was a human Universal. So it's an it's an amazing miraculous attainment
It's it's a miraculous attainment. Absolutely and you know, what we're supposed to be doing in the Universities is separating the wheat from the chaff
not
dispensing with everything as if it's chaff because we don't want to put in the effort to discriminate and
So it's easier. Well, it's just all corrupt
It's like no
it's not people aren't starving to death any more and
societies are increasingly free and children are dying in the massive numbers that they once died in and
People are people's life expectancy has doubled
Like things are going pretty well
don't muck it up and
We need to figure out why and we need to take stock of the things that we did in the past that were wrong
Obviously, but that doesn't mean that everything everyone did in the past was wrong
That's that that's not thinking that's just that's just reflexive resentment masquerading as intellectual superiority
There's nothing about it. That's good
When you've been incredibly generous with your time, can we wrap up? Let's just think through
What would we say in terms of people looking for solutions in?
Academia in the media in politics. How do we if you like
Start the movement to reclaim
What you called?
evidence based empirical decision evidence in decision-making in other words learn to think again and stop being us so
so emotional there's a place for emotion, but there's a place for thinking I
Think well, I mean if you're a university student
the first thing you want to note is that you're there to learn to think and to write and to
Read and to speak that's what you're there to do. And the reason you're there to do that is because that makes you incredibly
confident
Because you're going to have to communicate with people for the rest of your life
And if your communication has depth and clarity
Then you can see your way forward and you can bring other people aboard and you can do great things
And so it's super it's super
useful to get a real liberal arts education
because it can make you into a great communicator and thinker if
You're going to university read the great books and you can you can find
Professors who will teach you that but that's what you're there to do
You're there to spend four years
immersing yourself in the imitation of the greatest people that our culture has produced and if you think well
There were no great people. Well, then you might as well not go to university because
University is the storehouse of the thoughts of great people and if you dispense with a whole notion notion of great then
Maybe you're there too. I'm a political activist, but that's not university. That's something else that's like an ideological cult and
Maybe that's what you want. And and and I mean
You know, you'll pay the price for that one way or the other
But you even there's a university student you have to take on the burden of educating yourself to large degree
But you have to decide that that's what you want. And that's what you need in terms of your own personal life
Um, I have a program that I developed with my colleagues called the Future authoring program
It's itself authoring calm and it helps people develop a vision for their life
along about six fundamental dimensions family education
mental and physical health career
avoidance of temptation like drug and alcohol use
We tried to parse out our use of time you productive and meaningful use of time outside of work
we tried to parameterize a decent life and
Then to guide people through the process of imagining what their life could be like if they put it together
properly and you need to develop a vision for your life and a sense of who you could be if you were the character that
you could be and and
Thinking through that and articulating it is they're actually part of it should be part of a classic liberal arts education
Because the whole point of Education apart from the technical end
Which is important is to produce a noble citizen. That's the point not to produce a bloody political activist
Well, then you just wish would keep in mind that cuz
even a Chatswood that not a
Lot of those people. Most of them are not at university
So they're not excluded either from in any way shape or form from broadening their horizon
It's not like they're not doing important things like working men for example working people in general
I don't care what they're doing if they're working at a diner as a waiter. They're there
They're laying bricks or what working a forklift or they're plumbers or these people are bloody important
they build the infrastructure and there's a huge difference between a a
craftsman who takes pride and caring what he's doing and
Contributes to his family and the community in that nobility of work and someone who does shot in half hazard job
There's great nobility in genuine work
So and and I believe that you have just as much power. Let's say much as much authority as much clout as a
forthright and honest working person as you do as an intellectual and I mean you can be very
successful as a working person if you if you're
Diligent and honest and committed and competent and aiming up
because it look I do believe that each person is the center of the world and
You have what you need right at that Center and maybe you're not
Intellectual, but you're good with your hands and you're practical and solid and people can rely on you
It's like man
That's a big deal because then when their roof blows off in the middle of a storm
They can call you up and you're there in an hour and you put the damn thing back together and and and hooray for you
It's a all of these things are important. And so there's great nobility in working class work as far as I'm concerned
Well Jordan that's again a fascinating conversation from my perspective and
It's tremendous to be able to interact with somebody who cares passionately because that's what that's what they're picking up
I know it's not about you
You're actually trying to make a difference for people and you know, we're seeing this
I'm really disturbed by the way in which some of these movements were seeing at the moment of trying to divide men from women and
A lot of people getting men are getting this idea that somehow their masculinity is toxic
Well, you know
We don't say that when the brave young French policeman takes a bullet for a young woman and her daughter in a French supermarket
We celebrate that and I actually think that not all
But the great majority of men want to be Noble they know their flaws
As you said they've got to be honest about them. We all need to be honest
But they also have a big part of them if you like that divine spike
So does aspire divine spark that leads them to want to be
responsible noble people
Yes
And that's that's what women want for men too
so unless and as they've been damaged in their
Relationship so that they don't trust men at all and then are prepared to dispense with all of them which isn't helpful
But, you know men and women need to call to the nobility in each other and that is what they both want because you want
a stalwart companion by your side
know if you're a man you want someone you can trust and you can rely on it who will help guide you and and
and and care for you and to care for your children and all of that and to make a life with and if you're a
Woman you want a man that you can rely on and that's going to help you
Help you deal with the children and with the excess fragility that you have because of your pronounced role in reproduction
and that is what we want and to denigrate and to split men and women apart is is to
Damage humanity itself because it's not like we're all men are all women. I have sisters and a mother and a wife
and a daughter and
Women have husbands and sons and fathers. We're not separate and
to split us apart on on the basis of sex it's, it's well. It's
It's it's as pathological as a suicidal impulse or a murderous impulse or a genocidal impulse
none of that's good
It's not acceptable
But we're a hell of a lot better off than we were and things are getting better and we can do better yet
That's a way better story
We look forward very much to having you back on those shores
Very nice speaking with you again, and thank you very much for the opportunity. Thanks Jordan